[SPEAKER_00]: So, today's sutta is Samyutta Nikaya 22.81, which is just titled as Parileya.
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts by saying that the auspicious one was staying near Kosambi, in Gosita's monastery,
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the morning, he dressed, took his ball and entered Kolsumbi for alms.
[SPEAKER_00]: After the meal, on his return from alms round, he set his lodgings in order for himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking his ball and robe without informing his attendants of taking the leave of the Bhikkhu Saṅgha, he set out to go wandering alone with no companion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, not long after, the auspicious one left, one of the bhikkhus asked Ananda, well, told Ananda about the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Ananda said, when the auspicious one departs in this manner, it means he won't stay alone, and this time no one should go after him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the auspicious one, traveling stage by stage, arrived eventually at Perilea, where he stayed at the root of a sacred Sal tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: The several bhikkhus approached Ananda and exchanged pleasantries with him, and once the amicable and cordial talk was over,
[SPEAKER_00]: They asked him... well, they told him that it's been a long time since they heard a talk from the auspicious one.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would like to hear a dhamma talk from him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Ananda, together with those bhikkhus, went to Peralaya, where the Buddha was staying, bowed, sat down, and they asked him to give a dhamma talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'm not gonna read every introduction part, a paragraph.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question they asked him was,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, actually, one of the bhikkhus had a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: For one who knows and sees in which way is there an immediate destruction of influxes, of asavas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the Buddha knew what that Bhikkhu was thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he addressed them by saying, Bhikkhus, I've explained the dhamma thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've thoroughly explained the four establishments of recollectedness, the four right efforts, the four bases of spiritual ability, the five faculties, the five powers, the seven awakening factors, and the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is how I have explained the dhamma thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Though I've explained the dhamma thoroughly, still a certain bhikkhu present here has this thought, for one who knows and sees in which way is there immediate destruction of the influxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha answers it.
[SPEAKER_00]: An unlearned, ordinary person, who has not seen the Noble Ones, and is neither skilled nor trained in the teaching of the Noble Ones, who has not seen the Righteous Men, and is neither skilled nor trained in the teachings of the Righteous Men, regards form as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that regarding is an activation, saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the foundation, the origin, the birthplace, and the source of that saṅkhara, of that activation?
[SPEAKER_00]: For an unlearned, ordinary person, struck by feelings born of ignorance, pressure, craving, has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: That activation is born from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that activation is impermanent, determined, dependently originated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that craving too, that feeling, that pressure, that ignorance, are also impermanent, determined, and dependently originated.
[SPEAKER_00]: For one who knows and sees in this way, because there is the immediate destruction of the influxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it repeats the same for other aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps they do not regard form as self, they still regard self as possessing of form.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps they do not regard form as self, or self as possessing form, but they still regard form in self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that regarding is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or perhaps they do not regard form as self, or self as possessing form, or as form in self, but they still regard self in form.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whichever way you turn it around, there is self involved, there is the appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it says, yeah, now it goes for the aggregated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, perhaps, they don't regard form as self, self-possessing form, form in self, self in form, but they regard feeling as self, activations as self, consciousness as self, perception, activation, consciousness as self, but that regarding is an activation, and then repeats the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it says, or perhaps they do not regard form or feeling or perception or activations or consciousness as self, but they still have such a view that self and the cosmos are one and the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: After passing away, I will be permanent, everlasting, eternal, imperishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that eternalist view is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the foundation of that activation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it repeats the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the craving in regard to the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, perhaps, they do not regard form, or feeling, or perception, or activation, or consciousness as self, nor do they have such a view that self and cosmos are one and the same, and that after passing away, they will be permanent, everlasting, eternal, and imperishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, they have such a view that I might not be, and it might not be mine, I will not be, and it will not be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that annihilationist view is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the foundation of that activation?
[SPEAKER_00]: For one who knows and sees in this way, I mean, repeats the same and then it finishes, but that the one who knows and sees in this way, there is the immediate destruction of influxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the last part is, or perhaps they do not regard form, or feeling, or perception, or activations, or consciousness as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor do they have such a view that self and the cosmos are one and the same, and after passing away, they will be permanent, everlasting, eternal, imperishable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor do they have a view that I might not be, and it will not, it might not be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not be, and it will not be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, they have doubts and uncertainties.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're undecided about the true dhamma, that doubt and uncertainty, that indecision about the true dhamma is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the foundation of that activation?
[SPEAKER_00]: For an unlearned ordinary person struck by feelings born of ignorance pressure, craving has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: That activation is born from that, and that activation is impermanent, determined, dependently originated, and that craving too, that feeling, that pressure, passa, that ignorance are also impermanent, determined, and dependently originated.
[SPEAKER_00]: For one who knows and sees in this way, that is the immediate destruction of the influxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's get back to the top.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so the obvious thing here is
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much, obviously, it's the same core paragraph that repeats through the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, a patujana, an unlearned ordinary person, has not seen the Noble Ones, is not trained in the teaching, has basically made no effort in taming the citta, doesn't even know what that entails, let alone practice it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He regards his form as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, anything that can appear, anything that is manifested, which is the five aggregates, he, one way or the other, as the rest of the sutra explains, he regards as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: He appropriates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a matter of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you can just
[SPEAKER_00]: Learn the new things and then suddenly stop regarding form itself, stop regarding aggregates itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why this sutta, as I said, it's quite good because it actually shows you what the real problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, again, like, you know, I'm sure many people would have read the sutta and it's... it can almost seem like somewhat self-explanatory as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a sense that, oh, yeah, okay, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding is sankhāra, and the origin of sankhāra is feelings born of ignorance contact, and that's also impermanent, and then feelings born of ignorance contact give rise to craving, craving gives rise to that, and there it is, and I learned it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, if you approach the whole thing as something that needs to be seen here and now, not just outlined as like a theoretical truth,
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize that the very act of appropriation, so that's what it means, like, regarding, is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the very act of appropriation is due to the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when a puthujjana feels anything, and obviously, at any given time, he will feel, he will be feeling something, that pressure there,
[SPEAKER_00]: There is felt that the pressure that endures, craving in regard to that, is his appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, obviously, the natural question is, OK, so how do I stop the craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, if you follow the theoretical truth, well, remove the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there you go, Abhidhamma answered it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like, OK, so what is it that you do
[SPEAKER_00]: When there is a pleasant feeling enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, look at where does your motivation want to go, what are the general kind of... what is the general nature of those types of intentions in regard to that type of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it's an unpleasant feeling, what is it that your mind revolves around?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the main kind of defining attitude of that experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's kind of... Well, that's the part that's being overlooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the craving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, I can tell you, like, well, craving is something the animal does, but it's something that you don't see it as belonging to the animal, by default.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not like a...
[SPEAKER_00]: It can never be an object of your attention, something that you can just attend and perceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you can do two other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's all always overlooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you learn how to see craving as actually belonging to this living animal eye, the citta, then you won't appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't stop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not that the craving will stop, but it will stop being yours, that specific phenomenon of craving in regard to the feelings born of ignorance pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like I need to hunt down the craving in my experience and then stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like I'm seeing it and experiencing it every single day, left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to this, in regard to that, in regard to pleasure, in regard to pain, in regard to neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the phenomenon that is always overlooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you see it, you cannot help but feel like it is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's just how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like it's yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it that it feels like it's yours?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, as I said, pick up a... a... whatever you're currently feeling or, you know, if it's too subtle, bring up something unpleasant, something you don't like to think about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, look at the background of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how does... where does your mind lean towards or away from?
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's not like something you can do once and get an immediate answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like uncovering the attitude of your citta in regard to whatever's being felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like... think of it like, I don't know, you have a dog on a leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, my favorite examples.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a dog on the leash and it's just sitting or standing next to you, but it's not really pulling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not pulling on the leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then something comes, you know, in its field of vision, or it hears something, or it smells something, and it gets up, and it goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wants to go, and now you're feeling the tension in the leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that tension, in regard to whatever has been, you know, perceived, felt, intended, and so on, in regard to the aggregates, that is the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it, again, tension in and of itself, especially when you look at it in your own experience, it doesn't really have a subject, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you can immediately see.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you can tell to yourself, oh, this is my mind is doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in and of itself, the phenomenon of that, eh... tension within the pressure that's already there, that phenomenon is appropriated by default.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot not feel it, quote-unquote, as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: As something directly affecting me, something I have to deal with, either through allowing the dog to run after things, so the tension is released, or, you know, trying to get rid of it, or deal with it, or destroy it, or remove it, or deny it, whatever has kind of prompted it, so that the tension is released.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, for as long as you are acting out of that tension, one way or the other,
[SPEAKER_00]: You are regarding it as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are regarding it as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, if it weren't yours, it wouldn't be a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't worry about someone else's tensions, unless you feel affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you then stop being affected by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not going to start here again, because we spoke about it so many times, but the whole point of the gradual training is
[SPEAKER_00]: To lead towards that recognition, that even that taṇha is the animal's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's literally the dog that has seen something, it's pulling, it's pulling, but you don't notice that the pulling and the tension you feel, it's because of the dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is his doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think it's because of what's been seen, what's been heard, what's been said, or what hasn't been said, or because you didn't get enough of this, or you had too much of something else that you didn't want, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overlooking the obvious, that
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling that arose a kind of ignorance pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: By the way, ignorance pressure is just that, like not seeing the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not even noticing that it's the dog that jumped up and started dragging you around.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not even seeing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just see what the dog wants, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only thing you notice and that's the only thing you're concerned with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing that the craving is the doing of citta,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, truly recognizing, not just theoretically telling it to yourself, like, oh, this is not mine, but, like, genuinely seeing that, oh, there is a feeling arisen, and then there is that kick, or lean, or jump, and you are able to basically keep your distance from it as well, internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that can only be developed through actually gradually training the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no amount of information, meditation retreat, special insights that can just magically do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That space, you're literally carving out that space yourself through the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when there is enough of that space, then that kick, the scream, the bite of an animal is away from you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not as felt as acutely as before.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why this sutta is so interesting, is because you start carving out that space, you are undoing the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even the wrong views, as we see further down,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, all types of... see, regarding formless self or self as possessing form or form in self or self in form, all of those are pretty much the symptoms and the permutations and the spilling out of... spillings, basically, of the unresolved craving that's still being appropriated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could be philosophically bending your mind, like, endlessly, training it all you want, in terms of penetrating through the wrong views, and classifying them, and writing them down, and dividing them into subgroups, and learning about them, and making a whole network, and connecting all the dots and all the charts.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is... well, as the Sutta says, all of that is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Born out of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, born out of the same feeling, paired with ignorance pressure, that basically makes you overlook the citta, overlook its tendencies, overlook its direct tension in regard to pleasure, in regard to pain, in regard to neutral feeling, not dealing with it, not carving out that space.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of that is the result of that, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to undo the wrong views, you want to undo the sense of self, you want to undo the level of your dependence on these possessions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, well, you have to start
[SPEAKER_00]: Training in regard to the present enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to start uprooting the... uprooting the... well, not cultivating, not maintaining the attitudes born out of that craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, again, sense restraint, virtue, is not just something you keep externally, but something you train in to get closer and closer to the recognition of that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is what perpetuates the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's allowing the dog
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, to pull you, or even like letting it loose from the leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just, just like, oh, go for it, because when you're, when I hold you with a leash, I feel the tension.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I release it, I feel free and light and, and, and, and relieved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, it is good.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it isn't, and that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just regarding the aggregates itself, but then as the, as the sutta continues, you could see even the view
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody can actually... By the way, see, this is the wrong view now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's one of the annihilationist views that people often take as a caricature, thinking like, of course, nobody thinks this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But think about it here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's listed after somebody who is not regarding their aggregates as self anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody obviously would have trained citta sufficiently
[SPEAKER_00]: To not regard form, feeling, perception, activations of consciousness as self, means they have carved out some space, way more than your average Bhutujana, way more than your average Buddhist Bhutujana today.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, they might have a view that persists, which is either, well, after all this breaks apart,
[SPEAKER_00]: I shall remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sense of appropriation that has been inadvertently, wrongly maintained and cultivated is kind of assumed to continue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, it's assumed that it won't continue, like the next paragraph.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even those subtle views... Again, because somebody might be puzzled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, how do I figure this out?
[SPEAKER_00]: You might think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I actually figure this out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, let me think about these views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see... to understand them, to penetrate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like... you figure them out, by carving the space out away from the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you carve that space out by not acting out of craving, by not losing the sight of your citta, that you would have sufficiently seen, hopefully by then, through virtue, withdrawal from centrality, sense restraint and solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would see the movements within yourself,
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards pleasure, towards pain, and you would... doesn't matter how much you appropriate it, the time will come when it will feel like I am not doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what means like seeing the mind, seeing the signs of the mind, seeing its life independent of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like thinking about it theoretically or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what it means to see the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if somebody trained that and continues training it, even the view that, you know, this sense of self, this appropriation, that's kind of... not necessarily even bound with aggregates anymore, but it still has some standpoint in regard to it, like self and the world, like in the broadest sense, in the most general sense, all the peripheral, you know, the peripheral awareness and all the background, that's kind of regarded as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that will fade away if the same training continues.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the same taming of citta, of the same citta, of the same animal, in the same manner, just in regard to subtler things now, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then this, eh, the... Where was the other view?
[SPEAKER_00]: I scrolled past it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, let me find it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps, follow yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, yeah, no, that was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, neither that Self and Cosmos are the same, nor that somebody might not think that, might have even like, as I said, distanced themselves even from that peripheral and general awareness and the background of things being seen rightly, but they still might think that, oh, I might not be, might not be mine, so they're bringing, already bringing the sense of Self into question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not that they are even taking their sense of I am for granted anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's generally sense of self is being fully brought to question, but that thing is not questioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what this... because the Buddha said in other suttas that this is like the highest of the right views that Putujana can get to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the best he can get.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I might not be, and he might not be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he knows that he won't be permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the sense of that impermanence, the sense of that inevitable destruction, that is taken as something that you delight in.
[SPEAKER_00]: However subtly, that is taken as as an external standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why even that view here, it says, means basically that kind of implies a degree of appropriation, a degree of ownership, which means they're going to be a degree of self-involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, how do I fix that?
[SPEAKER_00]: The same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Continue training the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, you can imagine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first, you start keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: How will that feel from the point of view of somebody who doesn't keep the precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, that's gonna feel like, well, how does it say?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like an abyss.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a sudden precipice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, you know, a celibacy will feel like a sudden precipice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, basically, yeah, precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it stops feeling like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You train, you get closer, you maintain, you fail, you get back closer, da-da-da, you develop it, and it becomes a new base.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you train further now.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are other things within that, that the mind wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe wants company, wants, eh... interactions, wants distractions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start to recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start to recognize those tensions, those pulls of the dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop fueling them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop losing sight of the dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that you can eventually see it as the dog's doing, as citta's doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just tell it to yourself and adopt a view that this is cheetah's doing, therefore it's not my problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you still affected by any pressure, by any tension?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there still a compulsion to act towards pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Compulsion to get away from pain means it is your doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your regarding of it is still a self and that is an activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Born out of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, born out of that unchecked, untamed, still appropriated craving of the animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you work through that, and say now, the animal is not craving as much towards the feeling, because you've been training, you've been containing, you've been enduring things on the right level, as I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the internal space now that's discerned, so even when the animal jumps, you are not immediately, kind of, pulled with that jump.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, oh, it jumps.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It jumps.
[SPEAKER_00]: I remain untouched.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means to not suffer amid suffering, that I often say, and even the suttas, I think.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, basically, the suffering, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: the animal, still has these acts and tendencies, but you are completely, like, separated from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no, as I said, that immediate pang of, like, when an unpleasant feeling arises or, like, unpleasant news or frightening perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there is... the animal jumps, but you are not stabbed by it, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is... there is the space between...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how immediate, how fast, how unexpected feeling arises and how unexpected animal's reaction might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a space between all of that and your point of view, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that internal carving of space that I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, somebody would train rightly, somebody would then even undo these views, such as that, okay, well, this thing that I've developed, this most general thing, nothing specific anymore,
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll continue.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take that as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or recognize, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything will come to pass.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, you kind of take that as an external standpoint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that would fade away, if you continue the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, what you're left with is the undecided about the true dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you're kind of there, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there might be, now, the tendency to doubt
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: And instead of enduring the doubt on the right level, as I often say, you justify addressing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Addressing it through the means of coping and managing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, what does that addressing of doubt actually convey to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, convey that at least on that level, you still took for granted the arisen feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: There was unpleasant and you took for granted the attitude that you should get rid of it, resolve it and dispel the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you stop doing that long enough, you will teach the dog to come down even in the core of the most existential, life-threatening doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, by the way, it's not doubt about this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I said, like, how would a puthujjana, non-celibate puthujjana, feel when he takes on the eight precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the sutra says, it feels like an abyss, like a sudden precipice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, how would somebody, who does find comfort, when the unpleasant feeling of impermanence, of nothing is in my control, nothing is sure, everything could be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does that feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: For a putujana, or even for somebody who is who is maybe training and keeping the precepts, well, that feels like a new abyss now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why these these views, like, enacting out of these views, it's not just kind of, oh, because people are confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because it's an existential coping.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to cover that hole.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to cover that abyss.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to cover the block, that threat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mask it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the view that self and the cosmos are one and same, you start questioning that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna feel like an abyss.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might then come to terms that, okay, no, everything's coming to an end, and take that as a standpoint, and then start questioning that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, either way with those views, the reason why you would be doing it, holding the view, maintaining the view, is because, again, the underneath it all, there is an enduring feeling that you're resisting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather that you are accepting the resistance of the citta as your own.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing that it cannot be yours because there isn't enough space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when I say there isn't enough space between you and citta, means, like, I don't know, like, you don't, you're not even aware that you're holding the leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: The leash is tied to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just see the dog moving, you're being dragged.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see anything else in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why I say, you question that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You question that the self and cosmos are impermanent or that you question that, well, like, again, if you start finding pleasure that everything will end, find, finding comfort in that view, you start questioning that.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just so to... not again to find the answer whether it's true or not, but to stop taking for granted acting from the unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, by the way, pleasant feeling is also unpleasant in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant feeling towards sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't follow it, it's going to be felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not getting enough of the pleasure is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either way, dukkha will be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, learning how to not act out of it, because blindly accepting it, blindly following the direction that it offers, means regarding it as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That resistance, that tension, that leash pulling, means taking it up at face value, which means it is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what you say to yourself at the end of the day.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, what you are left with is now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you don't... you would have continued training and now these two possibilities of these two views, either that you will persist or you'll be destroyed, either way you find some solace in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You questioned it enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you left with now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you go used to that abyss of questioning your deepest existential safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you're questioning it, but then you fall into an answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you also learn that you shouldn't fall into an answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're questioning it, answers present themselves and you don't take them.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are you left with?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you're left with absolute, complete, through and through, top to bottom doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Existential doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you do now?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you feel justified in now explaining, resolving, plugging, covering up that doubt, dealing with it, you are the... well, you're falling into the type that's undecided about the true dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Came to the point of the existential doubt, but took that for granted and is trying to get rid of it, resolve it, act out of the feeling that's been regarded as self due to that craving that's not seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, that will be now the new abyss.
[SPEAKER_00]: The existential abyss of...
[SPEAKER_00]: The existential abyss of... Oh!
[SPEAKER_00]: I refuse to take any standpoint externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how satisfactory you might be in terms of
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, explaining the world, explaining the structure, explaining this or that, whichever, you know, whichever background you come from, in terms of your information, it's like, I'm not taking that for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I am actually choosing to be left with that doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is actually the surest thing of an unpolluted kind that I can experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither here nor there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, either mine or not mine, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ambiguous.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's not wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's the most unpleasant thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, that's why I said in those other old talks, like, nibbāna is the ultimate uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cultivate uncertainty in regard to your aggregates, in regard to your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't act out of them and train.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like... that's... that's nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the direct destruction of influxes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the last bit here that's mentioned in the suttas, like, they're undecided about true dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, not because, again, they haven't figured it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because when that existential doubt, when they came to that point, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: They chose to act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: They felt justified.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't apply the same principle that brought them to that point, which is putting everything into question and not taking it for granted and enduring it on the higher level and not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that was like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's not because, you know, you didn't... you feel like this or like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because it's felt, like, properly, like the abyss.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in your core of your being, it feels like you're hanging over a cliff and things could go either way in any direction and you have no say over it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's frightening and so on, but really, it's like the degree of suffering that would arise on account of being in that position is not determined by the cliff or by being on the cliff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's determined by how much you still depend on regarding self as form and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, how untamed your mind is, how hard your animal can still pull you, that is what is frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the dukkha of that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the animal is calm, it's the most liberating experience ever.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't owe anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody can owe anything to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody can do anything to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't exist for anybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody exists for you in that sense, in terms of connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, it's the most... it's the lightest, the most freeing, the most...
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncumbersome, unburdening experience ever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why the Buddha and other suttas changed that last bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: I might not be in a sense of, oh, it will not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if it were, it won't be for me, in other words.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he took that appropriation out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of corrected it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, that that sense of uncertainty, you know, as Ajahn Chah said, like, oh, not sure, not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just practice that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, practice that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through and through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just selectively.
[SPEAKER_00]: When things suit you, or as a coping management technique, when you don't get your way, then you recollect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not sure, not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not sure in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: No exception.
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to your sense of safety, your health, your life, all these are the perceptions that the suttas talk about that you need to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was that, like, that... that Zen...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it was, like, a Zen saying or some Zen monk wrote it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, before the practice, mountains were mountains, rivers were rivers, and, I don't know, forests were forests, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, during the practice, when he started practicing, like, mountains were not mountains, and forests were not forests.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he was doubting everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, when the mind calmed down within that doubt, he didn't give up the training, he was like, oh, mountains were mountains again, forests were forests, after the successful practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or like another, I think it was another Zen, maybe it was from the same monk, I don't know, when it was like, the practice kind of brings you to the point of... how do you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like, it feels like there is no sky above your head and no ground below your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, like, yeah, the pretty much the last stage of everything is in doubt, everything is felt in that sense, and the only thing you can do is try and not take it at face value and follow that that need, that pressure to resolve it, to address it, to deal with it, and instead you choose to stay with it on that on that abyss level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much kind of how you did from the start when you took on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to take on the abyss.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, again, gradual training.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't slot into it overnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same practice of creating space between you and that reaction, automated reaction of the animal, the inevitable flinch of the animal that you cannot but not take as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you don't see anything in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when craving is truly, correctly, when that movement, when that leaning of the animal is truly seen as, oh, like again, not your doing, you don't have to tell yourself, oh, this is not myself, therefore it's anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already felt not as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's already, eh... not going to be the dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the dukkha is when the craving is taken as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why taṇha is the reason for dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that taṇha, when that selfness of that craving, that regarding it as self, when the feeling arises, when that taṇha is not regarded as self, through right, correct, as I said, internal distancing, creating space between you and the citta,
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha cannot touch you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could factually recognize, oh, this is unpleasant, and the animal is scared, or it's excited, or it wants to do this, wants to do this, but none of that is sucking you in.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of that can get to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it's like seeing waves coming and knowing they will have to stop short of your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, you created enough space.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is... you might have doubted it initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like Sotāpanna can maybe initially think, oh, maybe I could still suffer in some ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: But repeatedly, actions, reactions of the citta cannot touch you and stop short of your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how big the waves are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you don't need to tell yourself to be confident about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're experiencing it over and over again, that you cannot be touched anymore, because the reason for you being touched was taking that, as I said, ultimate, habitual resistance of the animal towards pleasure, towards pain, wanting pleasure, taking that itself, because there wasn't enough space between the two of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, again, seeing the signs of the Mayācitta is the prerequisite for being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because how can you see the the space between you and the
[SPEAKER_00]: Split-second reaction of the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't even see the citta, that's not going to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, if one wants to be free from doubt, as in overcome doubt as a fetter, the last bit, I often, I mean, I said that before in many other talks, you have to
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, initially, you have to learn.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to collect the right information.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, you need to clarify the doubt and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you're doubtful about.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point will come when you will recognize that you're doing it out of compulsion, doing it out of trying to regain that mental sense of kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, satisfaction, safety, by removing that discomfort of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not really anymore about information and things you're doubtful about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about, as I said, taking for granted the attitude of trying to appease those uncomfortable feelings and replace them with something that citta deems more comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to free yourself from doubt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop fueling that behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you have to start training in regard to the uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how irrational, how big those waves get, you still mustn't be giving in to those wrong principles of acting out of it and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you go beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you're free from the fetter of doubt, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: that's how you become a sotāpanna, while still not necessarily be completely free from the hindrance of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you know, in regard to this or that, you are still accepting, acting out of doubt to some extent here and there, but not in that utmost, most general, core, fundamental, existential sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: When your own being, where your own sense of self is brought into question, you stopped panicking, you stopped running away, you stopped trying to blindly cover it up, and you stopped acting out of trying to manage that uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stayed with it long enough and the dog had no choice but to calm down and sit down and stop craving against it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you saw the space between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so, look, I mean, quickly, I can mostly answer all of it, but why does the Buddha describe every self of you as saṅkhara?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does he mean the one who's doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, it's all probably apparent by now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you're not doing it directly, but you're doing it indirectly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are doing it through allowing the acts of... Oh, yeah, the camera is going.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're doing it by allowing the acts of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fueling them, accepting them, going further out of them, adding more to them, you are maintaining the activation which is your sense of self, your rātavāda and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the second question was, why does the Buddha trace this activation back to ignorance in regard to feeling what is one ignorant of?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that craving that you're ignorant of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, taking it for granted, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, taking for granted that craving is pretty much something that everybody starts overlooking, starts as being overlooked, and it takes the whole gradual training, which is why the Buddha, you know, explained it the way he did, to be able to come to it, to actually see it as something done by the animal, not by you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we answered the third one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is abandoning explicit self-views insufficient if doubt and uncertainty still remains?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because it means that you are still maintaining the attitude, same attitude, in regard to the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: When doubt and uncertainty is present, unpleasantly it's felt, and you are basically still
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling justified in managing it, trying to get rid of it, acting out of it, and not seeing that as something that needs to be endured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so we got extra questions that people sent.
[SPEAKER_00]: One was the Sutta mentioned doubt and uncertainties.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could it be something as a momentum of citta, which caused doubting, even if the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's of course, it's a momentum of citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: The citta wants to get rid.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animal wants to deal with the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whether that discomfort is presented as precepts or the world that I thought will last forever, where I felt safe, will come to end,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, presented as nothing is certain, including the core of my being, it's discomfort of citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you are just blindly fueling the momentum of the animal that wants to get rid of the discomfort, you are then implicating yourself in everything else, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what this question said later, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of the uncompromised following of the direction of the right view means internally abandoning any safety in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any safety in the world and then any safety in a sense of dealing with uncertainty and feeling justified about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I said that before, like, uncertainty, it's not really like...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not painful in a, you know, in a kind of unbearable sense, you know, like, I don't know, somebody burning you with fire or stabbing you with knives.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you can't, you know, the brain just shuts down from pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just go unconscious.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not actually unpleasant, yet it's the most unpleasant thing there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That mental uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels far worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, not because it's objectively unpleasant, but because all the assumptions, needs and habits and lack of training of the animal and the pressure it puts on you because of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how does one know right view is truly right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, when, as I said, when the waves cannot get to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you found a perfect response to every wave, but because from where you're looking at them, it's simply untouchable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, when you have trained your citta sufficiently enough, you will know the right view as the right view, because you will not be able to suffer amidst the core of suffering, which was the the the quick animal reaction to pain or pleasure or neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the twitch, the subconscious reaction, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that cannot touch you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you know, oh, yeah, the right view is the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, amid suffering, I cannot be touched by suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, I would still prefer that the animal is calmer, therefore I should continue practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But fundamentally, in its core,
[SPEAKER_00]: There is, as I said, the space has been carved out and now it's like you cannot go back to what was before, which was you being confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who does the craving and what and just automatically regarding those attitudes as yours because you were prioritizing through your own views, getting rid of the pain as soon as possible, prolonging pleasure as long as possible and kind of ignoring and distracting yourself from neutral feeling as quickly as that was presented.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why was the translation of activation chosen?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because it kind of conveys, at least in part, a degree of your own doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, all the other... all the other kind of translations, formation, even determinations, is just too abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, activation is chosen because it's... it's... it comes from activities.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because of your perpetual taking up, engagement, proliferation of activities rooted in pursuing pleasure,
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting rid of the discomfort, ignoring the neutral feeling, your sense of self is there, active.
[SPEAKER_00]: Asavas are there, active.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dukkha is there, active.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's activated.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just to try and kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Re-establish, basically, that connection to, you know, your own practice, like living, and things that you do, and choices that you make.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is why these things are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it's just all formation and the form, it's kind of presumes, oh, it's something that happened back then, and it was formed, and therefore I must find some magical insight to unform it, or to find a way out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, no, you are maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why this sutta was so good, because it lists these views that people hold, you know, for the rest of their lives or lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in many ways, you kind of perpetuate the same stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because of your activities in regard to what's currently felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking those activities for granted, following them, proliferating them, that's why everything else is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole mass of suffering, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the center-self, that's how dukkha, that's how craving, that's how asavas are kept together, operating, affecting you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why.
[SPEAKER_00]: Got another question?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll add two parts to this question.
[SPEAKER_00]: When deeply contemplating impermanence, a sense of existential dread arises questioning what the point of it all is, and sometimes it brings up a lot of humility, but it feels like conceit as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: How does one work with both these states that arise?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, through questioning, depending on what state arises, you want to then see what is your current intention in regard to that state, in regard to that thing that are arising on account of certain contemplations.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I keep saying, that's why you always have to keep your motivation in check.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is, like, existential dread starts arising, what is it that the mind wants to do in regard to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you contemplate that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is he trying to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean... And actually ask yourself, like, when there is, like, anxiety or existential dread or anything, why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you were to ask yourself, what if I... what if this were to last forever, this... this feeling of uncertainty?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it a problem for me to stay with it for the rest of my life?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it's not stopping you from living,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not stopping you from eating.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not stopping you from breathing, drinking water, doing stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not stopping you from anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, I must deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where does that imperative come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, so how about I don't deal with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How about I live with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How about I learn to live with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about learn to live with it a bit longer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not immediately just try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you tame the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the ten perceptions of impermanence, loss and so on that the suttas talk about, that one should be frequently bringing up to their mind, provided, you know, the mind is already properly fenced off with established virtue and sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just... you're still acting out of body and speech coarsely and then start contemplating these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's probably gonna overwhelm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mind will probably overwhelm you because, like, literally you got a wild elephant
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't really fastened it and secured it in a pen area where you are safe, and you start agitating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you think will happen?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna go after you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, again, the whole gradual training is the way it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, if the animal feels like it's getting close to you, in your own mind, in a threatening manner, that's why we say, well, you gotta go back and check
[SPEAKER_00]: Are your precepts leaking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is your restraint not established?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you still overlooking stuff?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is what gives the power to the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what what kind of allows it to come close.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it might be scary, kicking and screaming, but if those... if the precepts are rightly trained in, intentions like habitually being revealed, not acting out of,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a fast, that is a solid anchor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the animal can be foaming in its mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know the length of the chain and you know it can't get you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as long as you don't stupidly reach out in its domain, you're safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's like right in your face.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it comes down and then starts to listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not before that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not gonna magically just suddenly obey you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, why would it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You've been feeding its whims for, well, this lifetime that you know, but, you know, many, many lifetimes before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that needs to be undone.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the kind of fortunate thing with human situation, according to the suttas, is that even in this relatively short lifespan of your average human life,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the most optimal time, the most optimal place to undo eons of bad habits of the citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, you can...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eons of feeding the wild animal, you could, in 20 years, calm it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: In these 20 years on this earth, you could calm it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the effort made in the human life is disproportionately effective than the effort to practice dhamma made in other realms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was like that sutta where those devas were living together on a... like a... almost like on a... on a... on a tip of a needle.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how little space they have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, they live in complete harmony and joy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Sariputta thought, oh, it's because they're keeping their minds in practice up there, and keep their minds lofty.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they said, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: We live here harmoniously, because when we were humans, we made the... the... the right effort to practice dhamma to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, we're bearing the fruit of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in... in...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't even specify the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the camera's gone again.
[SPEAKER_00]: They didn't even specify the time, how long they've been practicing as humans, but the point was... even if it was for a few years, basically, they practiced rightly, they tamed the mind rightly, and now, for eons, they're living in the, like, celestial pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Indicative of the amount of result you get for the effort made in the human realm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right effort made.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, then you can also extrapolate the opposite, the wrong effort made.
[SPEAKER_00]: The amount of bad results you get.